# **Maxwell Patterson**

mmpatterson94@gmail.com | 716-525-0522 | Boston, MA LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/maxwell-patterson/

#### **SUMMARY**

Data Science professional with experience in both client facing and non-client facing roles. Educational background includes an M.S. in Data Science from The University of Texas at Austin, as well as a B.S. in Mathematics and Physics from Dickinson College. Earned a professional certificate in Data Science from Northwestern University and have 7+ years of professional experience in data science and data analysis. Experienced in Python, R, SQL, and Tableau to create full-stack data solutions.

#### **EDUCATION**

### UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS- AUSTIN

Master of Science, Data Science

May 2024

 Coursework: Machine Learning, Probability & Statistics, Data Structures & Algorithms, Causal Inference, Regressions, Advanced Predictive Models, Natural Language Processing, Deep Learning, Data Visualization, Reinforcement Learning

### NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

Professional Certificate, Data Science & Data Visualization

February 2020

# **DICKINSON COLLEGE**

Bachelor of Science, Mathematics and Physics

May 2016

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

- **Programming**: Python (Pytorch, PySpark, MLflow, LangChain, NumPy, Pandas, Requests, Flask, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib), SQL (Databricks SQL, PostgreSQL, Microsoft SQL Server), R (ggplot, tidyverse, shiny, tidymodels), JavaScript (Plotly, D3, Leaflet)
- Machine Learning: Deep Learning Networks, Random Forests, Principal Component Analysis, K-Nearest Neighbors, K-Means, Regressions, Boosting Algorithms
- **Tools**: Databricks, Posit/RStudio, Alteryx, Tableau, Looker, Jupyter Notebooks, HTML5, CSS3, Git, SQL Server Management Studio, Amazon Redshift

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## SUFFOLK CONSTRUCTION

Roxbury, MA

Data Scientist

March 2022 - Present

Senior Data Analyst

- Built a smart search LLM chatbot that answers questions about Suffolk standard operating procedures, utilizing RAG architecture for document retrieval and a Shiny app for user interaction
- Created a productionized machine learning model in Databricks using MLflow that identifies construction projects likely to have a safety incident. The fiscal quarter after its initial implementation was the best quarter for incident rates in company history
- Analyzed historical project details to evaluate the company's ability to estimate staffing requirements on construction projects. We uncovered that our underestimations on staffing cost ~\$25M in revenue annually
- Built an application using Python and Tableau that shows the People & Culture team the closest employees to potential future job sites in order to assist in staffing teams

ZIPCAR Boston, MA

Data Analyst

September 2021 – March 2022

- Identified approximately \$70 of missing revenue per user in a dbt model that aims to estimate the average user's EBITDA over their first 90 days of membership
- Queried search data to find members in key markets that stopped searching for reservations on Zipcar's app after being active users of the service previously
- Built a Looker dashboard that allowed the billing team to measure success and billing accuracy via relevant KPIs

NIELSENIQ Chicago, IL

Analytical Framework Consultant

August 2019 – September 2021

• Led project that used Python and SQL to develop a reporting tool hosted at an API endpoint. Using product information from both database and API data sources, this reporting tool had built-in data validation functionality based on defined use cases, and it reduced manual analysis time by 95%

- Researched NielsenIQ product data to create database prototypes based on the needs of retailers and manufacturers in the CPG industry. Met with client SMEs to confirm databases meet contractual requirements
- Member of an efficiency team within the organization that aimed to identify manual processes that could be replaced with Python scripts to reduce the length of product delivery timelines

## TRILOGY EDUCATION SERVICES

Chicago, IL

Teaching Assistant, Data Visualization Program

April 2020 – August 2020

- Assisted students in a 24-week boot camp that teaches them Python, SQL, noSQL, JavaScript, Tableau, and machine learning concepts
- Reviewed and graded code submitted by students. Provided feedback in a timely manner

# REVENUE SOLUTIONS, INC.

Chicago, IL

IT Consultant

September 2016 – August 2019

Associate IT Consultant

- Received company award for excellence in communication with the client
- Used SQL Server to provide Production support for web applications that improve tax processing efficiency for three separate state, city, and county government agencies
- Frequently led meetings with client teams to discuss progress on product enhancements
- Designed software requirement specifications (SRS) for multiple custom interfaces involving ETL, providing access to more external data for clients

### **PROJECTS**

### WORLDWIDE EARTHQUAKE TRACKER

Github Link: <a href="https://github.com/mmpatterson/leaflet-earthquake-tracker">https://github.com/mmpatterson/leaflet-earthquake-tracker</a>

Link to Deployed Project: <a href="https://mmpatterson.github.io/leaflet-earthquake-tracker/earthquake-tracker/">https://mmpatterson.github.io/leaflet-earthquake-tracker/earthquake-tracker/</a>

- A site that displays information for earthquakes that have occurred within the last 7 days
- Using public data, plotted the location of each earthquake on a Leaflet map and scaled its size based on the severity of the event
- The map was created using Leaflet.js, and the API providing the data was made available by the United States Geological Survey